<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Roundup | Martin Foot]]></title>
  <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/blog/categories/roundup/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-21T22:33:31+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://mfoo.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Foot]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Link Roundup 26th March – 1st April]]></title>
    <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/blog/2012/04/01/weekly-link-roundup-26th-march-1st-april/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-01T16:33:18+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://mfoo.github.com/blog/2012/04/01/weekly-link-roundup-26th-march-1st-april</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A few weeks have gone since my last roundup, I have moved house and started working at a new job so haven't had much time. That said, here's a list of articles that I've found interesting over the past week. I've been getting into the 'devops' world recently (or at least using some of the domain tools and learning about scalable infrastructures), so many of the links are related.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Above is a video from HackADay about a new robot called the Sand Flea that <a href="http://hackaday.com/2012/03/31/sand-flea-literally-leaps-tall-buildings-in-a-single-bound/">has an impressive ability to jump over obstacles</a>. This could be very useful for robotic exploration in areas of difficult terrain.</p></li>
<li><p>A scientist has taken over 90,000 hours of video of his baby son via cameras all around the house in order to try and understand the learning of language and how we pick up and reproduce new words. I'm sure that I've seen a video of this before a few years ago, but now there is a lot more footage and similarly more interesting results. Read more about it including several videos <a href="http://www.fastcompany.com/1733627/mit-scientist-captures-his-sons-first-90000-hours-on-video">here</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>The <a href="http://weblog.rubyonrails.org/2012/3/30/ann-rails-3-2-3-has-been-released/">new version of Rails</a> has been released, which among other things addresses the <em>config.active_record.whitelist_attributes</em> issue that lead to the <a href="https://github.com/blog/1069-responsible-disclosure-policy">GitHub compromise</a> earlier this year.</p></li>
<li><p>Ranjib Dey has an <a href="http://ranjib.posterous.com/infrastructure-tooling-patterns">overview of the main common parts in web infrastructures</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Nikolay Sturm describes how we can <a href="http://blog.nistu.de/2012/03/04/reusability-in-configuration-management-systems/">apply object oriented principles such as the single responsibility principle and object extendability to configuration management systems</a> such as <a href="http://www.opscode.com/chef/">Chef</a>.</p></li>
<li><p>Nikolay was also featured on the <a href="http://www.foodfightshow.org/2012/03/episode-6-cookbook-reusability-with.html">Food Fight podcast talking about Cookbook reusability with Chef</a>.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.etsy.com">Etsy</a> have <a href="http://codeascraft.etsy.com/2012/03/13/making-it-virtually-easy-to-deploy-on-day-one/">a blog post </a>describing how their infrastructure can scale and pump out new VMs so that newly hired employees can push something to production on their first day. It's interesting seeing which tools they use and how they use them to facilitate this.</p></li>
<li><p>Netflix maintain a technical blog that describes some of the challenges they face and how they go about overcoming them. One in particular talks about <a href="http://techblog.netflix.com/2012/02/fault-tolerance-in-high-volume.html">fault tolerance in high volume distributed systems</a> and is a useful read for anybody designing a service based architecture.</p></li>
<li><p>John Vincent discusses requirements to be able to <a href="http://blog.lusis.org/blog/2012/03/06/graphs-in-operations/">accurately graph dependencies at macro and micro levels</a> in order to efficiently act upon changes in the dependency hierarchy.</p></li>
<li><p>Finally, in a less educational but more entertaining capacity, I have been reading several articles each trying to clarify what DevOps really is and if/why it's actually useful. Make what you will of the content. <a href="http://www.brunton-spall.co.uk/post/2012/03/13/what-is-devops-not/">What DevOps is not</a>, <a href="http://perfcap.blogspot.co.uk/2012/03/ops-devops-and-noops-at-netflix.html">Ops, DevOps and PaaS (NoOps) at Netflix</a>, and <a href="https://gist.github.com/2140086">a response to that post</a>.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekly Link Roundup 27th Feb - 4th March]]></title>
    <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/blog/2012/03/04/weekly-link-roundup-27th-feb-4th-march/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-04T12:49:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mfoo.github.com/blog/2012/03/04/weekly-link-roundup-27th-feb-4th-march</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I'm going to start taking notes of a few interesting articles/websites that I find each week in order to share them with others and preserve them for myself. And so begins Week One. Links will cover any article that I find interesting, but will largely be grounded in science and technology.</p>

<ol>
<li><p>An <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/badastronomy/2012/03/02/stunning-time-lapse-video-the-light-of-stars/">awesome <strong>time-lapse video of night skies</strong></a> was posted the other day (embedded above). I love stunning videos of nature and this is no exception.</p></li>
<li><p>Some scientists as part of a Russian research team have <a href="http://news.nationalgeographic.com/news/2012/02/120221-oldest-seeds-regenerated-plants-science/?source=link-tw20120229news-plant">reportedly managed to <strong>germinate seeds that were found under 124 feet (38 meters) of permafrost</strong></a> (annoyingly, it doesn't link to the source journal article), which were determined to be around 32,000 years old by radiocarbon dating. The article describes how knowledge of unfreezing and re-cultivating these seeds could benefit places such as the Svalbard Global Seed Vault.</p></li>
<li><p>A new <a href="http://www.mozilla.org/en-US/collusion/">experimental plugin for Firefox</a> called Collision that allows you to <strong>visualise the connections between services that websites use to track you while you are online</strong>. It's certainly quite eye-opening about the number of websites that record your usage data and statistics. Mozilla writes: <em>Not all tracking is bad. Many services rely on user data to provide relevant content and enhance your online experience. But most tracking happens without users' consent and without their knowledge. That’s not okay. It should be you who decides when, how and if you want to be tracked. Collusion will be a powerful tool to help you do that</em></p></li>
<li><p>The <a href="www.raspberrypi.org/">Raspberry Pi foundation</a> also recently announced that they have <strong>started shipping A and B model Raspberry Pis</strong>, although they are currently out of stock in both RS and Farnell. Using these distributors allows for a much higher production rate that scales to demand, and will help reduce shipping costs for people due to worldwide distribution networks. Can't wait until they are back in stock.</p></li>
<li><p>A <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/loom/2012/03/02/tongue-parasites-to-people-of-earth-thank-you-for-your-overfishing/">scary post that describes </a><strong><a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/loom/2012/03/02/tongue-parasites-to-people-of-earth-thank-you-for-your-overfishing/">a fish parasite</a> that enters the gills of a fish, devours its tongue, then positions itself in place of the tongue</strong>. Just the picture alone is creepy! Nature is awesome.</p></li>
<li><p>A <a href="http://www.bbc.co.uk/iplayer/episode/b01cywtq/Horizon_20112012_The_Truth_About_Exercise/">BBC Horizon show</a> about <strong>what exercise really does and the best ways of getting the maximum benefit</strong> (probably UK only). This is coupled with <a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/80beats/2012/03/02/just-3-days-of-lazing-around-will-weaken-your-ability-to-regulate-blood-sugar/">a post from DiscoverMagazine</a> on a new study that suggests <strong>healthy people will develop higher blood sugar after only three days of a sedentary lifestyle</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>A <a href="http://www.markshuttleworth.com/archives/939">post from Mark Shuttleworth</a> that shows the <strong>new HUD functionality coming in Ubuntu 12.04</strong>.</p></li>
<li><p>A good collection of <a href="http://www.dextronet.com/micro-isv-insights/2012/01/30-books-everyone-in-software-business-should-read-and-why/"><strong>30 books that everyone in the software business should read and why</strong></a>. I know that five or six of these are already on my Amazon wishlist for when I have the time, and it's definitely a list worth looking at.</p></li>
<li><p>An <a href="lists.busybox.net/pipermail/busybox/2010-December/074114.html">interesting explanation of <strong>why the bin, sbin, usr/bin, and usr/sbin folders exist</strong> in Unix</a> as well as why the programs located in each exist where they do.</p></li>
<li><p>A <a href="http://highscalability.com/blog/2012/2/13/tumblr-architecture-15-billion-page-views-a-month-and-harder.html">detailed and very interesting article describing Tumblr's scalable architecture</a> and how it allows them to serve '500 million page views a day, a peak rate of ~40k requests per second, ~3TB of new data to store a day, all running on 1000+ servers'.</p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
