<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: biology | Martin Foot]]></title>
  <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/blog/categories/biology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-01-22T22:12:00+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://mfoo.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Martin Foot]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction to Genetics and Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://mfoo.github.com/blog/2013/01/01/introduction-to-genetics-and-evolution/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-01T22:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://mfoo.github.com/blog/2013/01/01/introduction-to-genetics-and-evolution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the things that I wanted to do in 2012 was to learn more about genetics
and the process of evolution. I never had much of an interest in biology until
I took a course by (<a href="http://legacy.www.ecs.soton.ac.uk/about/klaus-peter.php">Dr Klaus-Peter Zauner</a>)
at university on how engineering principles can be applied to, and indeed
derived from, biological processes. Fascinated by the fact that we're ever
closer to understanding the systems and pathways that control growth and
interactions within the body, and the knowledge that we are already able to
design systems to perform tasks for us, I now see biology as one of the
ultimate goals for engineering. I would highly recommend anybody who has a
computer science or engineering degree/background to read into this. As a
software engineer I'm constantly learning new things. There's always something
interesting to read or learn about... but it's usually not an entirely new
frontier. Biological computation is just that.</p>

<p>In the interests of learning, I recently completed a 10 week free online course
called the <a href="https://www.coursera.org/course/geneticsevolution">Introduction to Genetics and Evolution</a> by Professor
Mohamed Noor and his assistants at Duke University in North Carolina. It
equated to 1--2 hours a week so was not too much of a commitment, but was a lot
of fun. The course is running again shortly and I would thoroughly recommend it
to anybody willing to learn.</p>

<p>Here's an example of a species we studied called the Lampsilis Mussel when
studying camouflage and the extend that evolution can be observed in the wild.
Just a fascinating taster of some of the course material!</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/I0YTBj0WHkU"
frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
